Inventory of the Wabash Railway Records 1836-1954
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Wabash Railway Records 1836-1954
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2003-001
5.5 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Wabash Railroad began with a 12-mile stretch of track between Meredosia and Morgan City, Illinois, which was constructed in 1838. The track was commonly known as the Northern Cross, and the Northern Cross Railroad was created from it. The company slowly expanded from the original 12-mile line, reaching the Indiana state border in 1856. During that time the railroad underwent receivership from a group of enterprising businessmen from Indiana and Ohio who wanted to create an unbroken link from Toledo, Ohio to the Mississippi River. Two railroads were formed under the same management to complete the task, eventually combining in 1856 as the Toledo, Wabash, and Western Railroad.
The company that began as the Northern Cross Railroad officially became known as the Wabash Railway in 1877, when the company reorganized itself from the Toledo, Wabash and Western Railroad due to poor economic conditions. Despite the struggling economy, the Wabash continued to push north towards Chicago. In the years that followed, the Wabash Railway was successful in running lines through Chicago, Detroit, and eventually St. Louis in time for the Louisiana Purchase Exposition in 1904.
The Wabash Railway was forced into receivership during the Depression and emerged in 1942 as the Wabash Railroad. The company continued service until it was bought by industry giant Norfolk and Western in 1964.
Scope and Content Information
The Wabash Railway Records (1836-1954) are comprised primarily of Financial Records (1895-1942) and Chairman's Files (1871-1931). Financial Records consist of documents compiled for the Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC), reports from bank affiliates, and statements of expenditures. Chairman's Files include acquisition papers, Wabash company stock, and Executive Committee meeting minutes.
In addition to Financial Records, the collection contains Wabash Historical Files (1915-1941) that include original certificates of incorporation, deeds, charts showing corporate history, and detailed maps of Wabash lines. In addition, the Oversize Materials (1836-1930) series contains a report on the history of original cost of the Wabash to 1919, which details expenses of the company at its inception. Also included in the Oversize Materials are original deeds, agreements, and statements of call loans and collateral.
The collection also documents the Wabash Railway's strategic acquisitions of railroads in order to expand its Midwestern territory to the north and east. These papers include files from railways associated with the Wabash, Grand Trunk Railway in Canada, the Pittsburgh and West Virginia Railway, as well as articles of consolidations and mortgages.
Arrangement
Some files have been rearranged to facilitate description of the collection, but the majority remain in their original order.
Contents List
- Wabash Historical Files, 1915-1941
  - Original Certificate of Incorporation, Deed, and listing on the New York Stock Exchange, 1915 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Plan and agreement of reorganization of the Wabash Railroad to Wabash Railway, used in the Equipment Trust Hearing, 1915 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Deeds to the Wabash Railway, 1915-1941 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Charts showing corporate history of Wabash Railroad, June 30, 1919 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Collection of maps detailing the entire Wabash network, general correspondence included, 1918, 1929 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Wabash Railway Report: Corporate and Financial History, December 31, 1939 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Summary of properties released, condemned, and abandoned; includes map of Wabash lines, 1940-41 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Valuation Papers, 1871-1940
  - From the Chairman of the board; general file dealing with the Wabash Railway evaluation, 1871-1930 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - From the Chairman of the board; general file pertaining to the Wabash Railway valuation by the ICC, 1872-1930 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Report: Valuation of Railway Property in the United States, by Edgar Clark, ICC Chairman, June 18, 1921 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Before the ICC: testimony of H.E. Hale in the matter of valuation of property of the Mobile and Ohio Railroad, May 17, 1922 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Presidents Conference Committee: direct testimony and cross examination of H.E. Hale on the valuation of the New York, Ontario, and Western Railway, October 23, 1922 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Stenographers minutes before the ICC, valuation of the Wabash Railway, oral agreement, May 31, 1928 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Valuation docket heard before the ICC - valuation of the Wabash Railway, October 7, 1931 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Report: Valuation of Railroads, 1937-40 (Box-folder 2-15)
- Chairman's Files, 1871-1931
  - Acquisitions, 1890, 1928-30
    - Application by the Wabash Railway in the acquisition of the Lafayette Union Railway, before the ICC, 1890, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-16)
    - Acquisition of control, through lease, of the Lafayette Union Railroad, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-17-19)
    - Cumulative report; acquisition of the Lafayette Union Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 2-20)
    - Acquisition of the Lake Erie and Fort Wayne Railroad by Wabash Railway, 1904-29 (Box-folder 2-21)
    - Memorandum detailing the facts with the merger between the Pennsylvania Railroad and Wabash Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Wabash Stock and Company Stock of Interest, 1928-30
    - General file concerning the stock of other railroads, includes general correspondence, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-23)
    - General correspondence relating to stock dividends, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-24)
    - Correspondence pertaining to the buying and selling of company stock, includes contract of capital stock between Wabash Railway and the Terminal Railroad Association of St. Louis, 1929 (Box-folder 2-25)
    - Correspondence letters referring to the annual meeting of stockholders, 1929 (Box-folder 2-26)
    - Wabash Railway Preferred Stock A, 1929 (Box-folder 2-27)
    - General correspondence relating to stock dividends, 1929 (Box-folder 2-28)
    - Stock owned by the Wabash Railway - includes correspondence letters, 1929 (Box-folder 2-29)
    - Correspondence between Wabash Railway and Buell & Co. on the matter of purchasing stock from the Toledo, Peoria, & Western First Mortgage, 1929 (Box-folder 2-30)
    - Secretary's File: shares of Wabash stock held by Salkeld and Company, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-31)
  - Executive Committee, 1907, 1922-31
    - Extracts from meeting minutes of the Executive Committee of Board of Directors, includes annual meeting minutes from Wabash stockholders, 1907, 1930-31 (Box-folder 2-32)
    - Report on grading the Engineering Committee of the President's Conference Committee, August 1922 (Box-folder 2-33)
    - Authorizations by the executive committee of expenditures for miscellaneous additions and betterments, January-June, 1929 (Box-folder 2-34)
    - Authorizations by the executive committee of expenditures for miscellaneous additions and betterments, July-December, 1929 (Box-folder 2-35)
    - Wabash directors meetings, includes correspondence, 1929 (Box-folder 2-36)
    - Matters on hand for the Wabash executive committee meeting, 1929 (Box-folder 2-37)
  - General Chairman's Files, 1922-30
    - Contract between Wabash Railway and American Car & Foundry Co., 1922-29 (Box-folder 2-38)
    - From the Chairman of the board; includes reports, confidential memorandums, financial charts, correspondence, statements, 1927-31 (Box-folder 2-39)
    - Collateral and other notes; includes papers from the loan of the Wabash to the Ann Arbor, 1927-29 (Box-folder 2-40)
    - Earnings and expenses, estimates and statements of the Wabash Railway, includes newspaper clippings, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-41)
    - Correspondence between Wabash Railway and several other railroad companies regarding the distribution of annual reports, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-42)
    - Inquiry on special deposits made by Wabash Railway, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-43)
    - Income account forecast for the Wabash Railway; includes financial charts and correspondence, 1928-29 (Box-folder 2-44)
    - Consolidations; includes newspaper clippings and correspondence, 1929 (Box-folder 2-45)
    - Memorandum and correspondence referring to the hiring of transfer agents by the Wabash Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 2-46)
    - Financial forecasts of the Wabash Railway, charts, 1929 (Box-folder 2-47)
    - Minutes of organization meeting of the board of directors of the Railway Express Agency, 1929 (Box-folder 2-48)
    - Lease made between the Wabash Railway and the St. Mary's Machine Company covering real estate located in St. Charles, Missouri, 1929 (Box-folder 2-49)
    - President's monthly letters, 1929 (Box-folder 2-50)
    - Estimated income accounts and financial forecasts, 1929 (Box-folder 2-51)
    - Suspense accounts, includes general correspondence, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-52)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-53)
    - Estimated income accounts for the Wabash Railway; includes correspondence and income charts, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-54)
    - Monthly statement of unpaid vouchers, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-55)
    - Monthly capital authorizations not exceeding five thousand dollars, for any one project, 1929-30 (Box-folder 2-56)
- Files from Railways Associated with the Wabash, 1886-1940
  - Grand Trunk Railway, 1898-1940
    - Original agreement between the Grand Trunk Railway and Wabash Railroad - includes Wabash time table and a map of Grand Trunk Railway system and connections, 1898-1901 (Box-folder 2-57)
    - Maps detailing Wabash Railway and Grand Trunk Railway lines: Windsor to Niagara Falls, Ontario, and Black Rock, New York - used in Berry Valuation, July 1, 1913 (Box-folder 2-58)
    - Personal correspondence between the Canadian National Railways and Wabash Railway, 1916-28 (Box-folder 2-59)
    - Income accounts of the Grand Trunk Railway Western Lines, includes correspondence letters, 1917-26 (Box-folder 3-60)
    - Brief of indenture and agreement between Grand Trunk Railway and Wabash Railway, December 10, 1919 (Box-folder 3-61)
    - Official report on the Grand Trunk Railway Arbitration, 1920-40 (Box-folder 3-62)
    - Charts showing interest rental on property operated under trackage rights with Canadian National Railways related to Grand Trunk Railway, 1928-29 (Box-folder 3-63)
    - Financial analysis of suspension and international bridges on Wabash lines related to Grand Trunk Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 3-64)
  - Pittsburgh and West Virginia Railway Annual Reports, 1917-54
    - First annual report through the seventh, 1917-23 (Box-folder 3-65)
    - Eighth annual report through the fourteenth, 1924-30 (Box-folder 3-66)
    - Fifteenth annual report through the 21st, 1931-37 (Box-folder 3-67)
    - 22nd annual report through the 27th, 1938-43 (Box-folder 3-68)
    - 29th annual report through the 34th, 38th, 1945-50, 1954 (Box-folder 3-69)
    - Extra copies, 1923-54 (Box-folder 3-70-72)
  - Articles of Consolidation, 1889-1922
    - Articles of Consolidation for the Toledo & Western Railroad and other Wabash lines - includes the states of Illinois, Missouri, and Ohio - includes comprehensive report on the Wabash Railroad Articles of Consolidation, 1889-1913 (Box-folder 3-73)
    - Articles of Consolidation for the Toledo & Western Railroad and other Wabash companies - includes Articles for Indiana and Michigan; also includes report "Assent of Stockholders to Articles of Consolidation" 1889-1913 (Box-folder 3-74)
    - Articles of Consolidation between the Toledo Western Railway and the Wabash Railway, 1913 (Box-folder 3-75)
    - New York, Chicago, & St. Louis Railroad - Articles of Consolidation - 3 copies, December 28, 1922 (Box-folder 3-76)
  - Mortgages, 1901-40
    - Papers from the first mortgage of the Toledo & Chicago Railroad; deed of trust between Wabash Railway and Knickerbocker Trust Co., 1901, 1939-40 (Box-folder 3-77)
    - Brunswick & Chillicothe Railroad - First Mortgage Bonds, 1902-18 (Box-folder 3-78)
    - Correspondence between the Wabash Railway and Central Union Trust Co. regarding the Detroit and Chicago Extension First Mortgage, 1916-29 (Box-folder 3-79)
    - First mortgage of the Kansas City, Excelsior Springs & Northern Railway, under the Wabash Railway, 1921-29 (Box-folder 3-80)
    - Kansas City Terminal Railway proposed refunding and improvement mortgage, under the Wabash Railway, 1930-31 (Box-folder 3-81)
  - Other Railways and Institutions, 1886-1929
    - Detroit and Chicago Extension Bonds, includes general correspondence, 1913-15 (Box-folder 3-82)
    - Correspondence between Wabash Railway and Ford Motor Company on the matter of obtaining a condensed profile of the Detroit, Toledo, & Ironton Railroad, 1925, 1929 (Box-folder 3-83)
    - General correspondence to other companies regarding the Wabash annual meeting; includes newspaper clippings, 1929 (Box-folder 3-84)
    - Material from other railroads and institutions concerning the making of railroad maps and selling of stock, 1929 (Box-folder 3-85)
    - Correspondence between Wabash Railway and Col. W.J. Wilcus on the matter of obtaining condensed profiles of various railroad companies, 1929 (Box-folder 3-86)
    - F.B. Wilcox & Company - memorandums and letters to potential stockholders, 1929 (Box-folder 3-87)
    - Remittances made to the New York and St. Louis offices by the local treasurer, 1929 (Box-folder 3-88)
    - General correspondence to other companies regarding the Wabash annual meeting, includes newspaper clippings, 1929 (Box-folder 3-89)
    - Graphs, charts, and correspondence pertaining to the study of operating results for thirteen railroad companies in comparison to the Wabash Railway, 1929-30 (Box-folder 3-90)
- Wabash Railway Financial Records, 1895-1942
  - ICC Files, 1925-42
    - Finance dockets and reports from the ICC concerning the Reconstruction Loan made by Wabash Railway, 1925-32 (Box-folder 4-91)
    - Finance docket from the ICC in the matter of the future conduct of the express business; includes agreement between the American Railway Express Co. and agents for participating railroads, 1928-29 (Box-folder 4-92)
    - ICC docket concerning the consolidation of railroads to a limited number of systems, 1929 (Box-folder 4-93)
    - Finance docket before the ICC on the matter of additional lines under Wabash control, 1929 (Box-folder 4-94)
    - Finance dockets and reports from the ICC concerning the Reconstruction Loan made by Wabash Railway, 1932-34, 1939 (Box-folder 4-95)
    - Wabash Railway Equipment Trust, Series A - includes original copies of bonds and a finance docket from the ICC, 1942 (Box-folder 4-96)
  - Banks, 1928-42
    - Indenture made between the Bankers Trust Co. of New York and Wabash Railway, January 10, 1928 (Box-folder 4-97)
    - Collection of correspondence and deposit cards from various banks in U.S. and Canada - 2 folders, 1928-29 (Box-folder 4-98)
    - Promotional pamphlets, financial statements, correspondence, reviews, messages to investors from various banks, sent to Wabash Railway - 2 folders, 1928-29 (Box-folder 4-99)
    - Correspondence between the Equitable Trust Company of New York and Wabash Railway on the matter of value of securities held as collateral in Wabash loans to brokerage firms, 1929 (Box-folder 4-100)
    - Correspondence between the Equitable Trust Company of New York, the Chemical Bank & Trust Company, and the Wabash Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 4-101)
    - Correspondence referring to the request to purchase Equipment Trust Notes from certain financial institutions, 1929 (Box-folder 4-102)
    - Lease of railroad equipment from the Bank of North America to Wabash Railway, 1929 (Box-folder 4-103)
    - Statement: Chase National Bank of New York vs. Wabash Railway, before the District Court of the United States, includes Wabash financial charts, 1938-40 (Box-folder 4-104)
    - Equipment statistics of units on hand, comprised by the Central Hanover Bank & Trust Co., April 15, 1940 (Box-folder 4-105)
    - Wabash Equipment Trust, Series A, 1942 (Box-folder 4-106)
  - Reports, 1908-41
    - Presidents Conference Committee: report - "Depreciation Rates, Locomotives" 1908, 1918 (Box-folder 4-107)
    - Report: Trend of Prices, from the office of the Vice Chairman, Eastern Group, Presidents' Conference Committee, September 1, 1928 (Box-folder 4-108)
    - Correspondence and reports relating to Wabash coupons that were destroyed in a fire in St. Louis in 1929, 1928-30 (Box-folder 4-109)
    - Statistical information on the Hannibal Bridge in Missouri, 1928, 1937 (Box-folder 4-110)
    - Report: Swell on Dredged Materials: Comparing Scow Measurement with Place Measurement, from the office of the Engineer, Eastern Group, August 21, 1941 (Box-folder 4-111)
  - Expenditures, 1929-30
    - Statement of actual and proposed expenditures covering additions and betterments to roadway and structures and equipment for which bonds may be issued - includes correspondence and report on expenditures made on completed projects, 1929 (Box-folder 4-112)
    - Expenditures made on completed projects for the period January 1, 1928 to September 30, 1929, but not yet capitalized, covering additions and betterments to roadway and structures and equipment, 1929 (Box-folder 4-113)
    - Collection of correspondence referring to the payment of bills and expenses, 1929 (Box-folder 4-114)
    - Correspondence pertaining to the Executive Committee detailing expenditures made in maintaining roads and equipment, 1929-30 (Box-folder 4-115)
  - Equipment Lien, 1927-40
    - Reconstruction Finance Corporation (RFC): papers from the Equipment Lien matter, compiled by Russell L. Snodgrass, 1927-28 (Box-folder 4-116)
    - Equipment Lien Hearing, exhibit introduced by compliant, statement of equipment on hand as of December 31, 1938; statement includes number of units, date built or purchased, type and road number, 1938-40 (Box-folder 4-117)
  - General Company Files, 1927-41
    - Financial situation of the company from October 1, 1927 to September 30, 1928; includes correspondence and financial charts, 1927-29 (Box-folder 4-118)
    - Statement showing in detail amounts in general balance sheet account 711, special deposits, 1929 (Box-folder 4-119)
    - Correspondence referring to the auditing of accounts, 1929 (Box-folder 4-120)
    - Statement of securities pledged and unpledged, and securities owned, 1929 (Box-folder 4-121)
    - Correspondence letters and solicitations sent to stockholders, 1929 (Box-folder 4-122)
  - Income Account and Financial Exhibits, 1895-99, 1905-09 (Box 5)
    Collection of financial reports of the Wabash Railway. Reports are comprised by the auditor and divided by month.
- Books, Ledgers, 1904-32 (Box 6)
  - Book entitled "Valuation Orders" includes maps and profiles, summary of company purchases, inventories, and several pamphlets from the ICC concerning map specifications, 1914-16
  - Official German Report of American Railroads, by Hoff and Schwabach. 1906
  - Book entitled "Miscellaneous Papers" includes agreements, briefs, reports, and Reorganization Committee notices, 1904-16
  - The W.M. Corporation journal, 14 written pages. Includes deposits and withdrawals from the company. 1931-32
  - The W.M. Corporation ledger, 24 written pages. Includes expenses, cash advances and deposits, and accrued interest payable, 1931-32
- Oversize Materials, 1836-1930 (Box 7)
  - History of Original Cost to Date to 1919; includes historical map of the Wabash Railroad through June 30, 1919, 1836-1919
  - Original receipts from the construction department of the Toledo, St. Louis, and Kansas City Railroad, in very fragile condition, 1886-1888
  - Deeds, agreements, and correspondence pertaining to the early development of the Wabash Railroad, 1881-1904
  - Promotional pamphlets, financial statements, reviews, etc. from various banking institutions, 1928-30
  - Statement of call loans and collateral, 1929